{"tossups": [{"question": "In the prelude to this event, Ian Holbourn befriended a young Avis Dolphin. The HMS<em> Juno</em> left Cork Harbor to assist in the aftermath of this event but was called off by the Admiralty. The handling of this event prompted William Jennings Bryan to resign as Woodrow Wilson\u2019s Secretary of State. The United States joined World War I in the aftermath of, for the point, what 1915 attack on a British liner by a German U-Boat?", "answer": "the sinking of the RMS<b> Lusitania</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A ship carrying this commodity lost its sails in a storm off the coast of Japan, eventually bringing the three sailors to the American coast via the Kuroshio Current. Cao Cao [sow sow] of the Wei Dynasty conquered a movement known as the Five Pecks of this commodity during the Three Kingdoms period. The first domestication of this crop occurred in the Yangtze River valley. For the point, name this staple grain that is grown in paddies throughout Asia.", "answer": "<b> rice</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a novel set in this city, Esperanza and her family dream of living in an upper class neighborhood that they visit every Sunday. The Younger family attempts to move out of this city\u2019s fictional Clybourne Park in<em> A Raisin in the Sun</em>. Richard Wright wrote about the poor and disillusioned Bigger Thomas living in this city\u2019s South Side. For the point, name this large Midwestern city, the home of Gwendolyn Brooks, who wrote<em> For Illinois, 1968</em>.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "The Hittite king Suppiluliuma I may have sent a son to marry this woman, only for him to die en route to Carchemish. This woman may have assumed a male alter-ego, Smenkhkare [smenk-kah-ray], to rule after the death of her husband at the end of the Amarna Period. With her husband, this woman promoted the monotheistic faith of Aten. For the point, name this wife of Akhenaten who possibly ruled as an early Egyptian pharaoh.", "answer": "<b> Nefertiti</b> (accept<b> Neferneferuaten</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A way to sequence this material was invented by Frederick Sanger. In the central dogma of molecular biology, this material is transcribed. Okazaki fragments are formed when this material is replicated. A study conducted by Rosalind Franklin and published by Francis Crick and James Watson showed that this material takes the form of a double helix. For the point, name this biological molecule, found in the nucleus of the cell, that stores genetic information.", "answer": "<b> DNA</b> (accept<b> Deoxyribonucleic acid</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "In the prelude to this event, George Rappleyea attempted to hire H.G. Wells, but Wells refused as he had no legal training. The defendant in this case intentionally violated the Butler Act in order to force this trial to occur. Clarence Darrow defended one side in this case but failed to defeat the arguments of William Jennings Bryan. For the point, name this 1925 trial in which a Tennessee teacher was fined $100 for teaching evolution.", "answer": "<b> Scopes</b> Monkey Trial (accept State of<b> Tennessee</b> v. John<b> Scopes</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "While in Bristol, a supporter of this movement attacked Winston Churchill with a dog whip. The Cat and Mouse Act, which allowed for the temporary release of prisoners, was passed after supporters of this movement were force-fed during hunger strikes. Emmeline Pankhurst founded the Women\u2019s Franchise League in support of this movement. For the point, name this 20th century movement which sought to double the voting population in the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b> women\u2019s suffrage</b> (accept answers related to<b> women</b> getting the right to<b> vote</b>; prompt on suffrage)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man founded the League of Gileadites to prevent the capture of former slaves through the Fugitive Slave Act. In response to the Sacking of Lawrence, this man killed five settlers in the Pottawatomie Massacre. Marines led by Robert E. Lee defeated this man at a federal armory in Virginia. For the point, name this abolitionist who was hanged after his raid on Harpers Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Near the start of this event, Jules Brunet served as a military adviser to the breakaway Republic of Ezo. During this event, the national government created the hyojungo, a standardized dialect meant to unify the country. The Boshin War started this event, during which the last Tokugawa Shogun fled Osaka Castle. For the point, name this 1868 event in which the namesake emperor restored imperial power in Japan.", "answer": "<b> Meiji</b> Restoration", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2017, this painting was used as the centerpiece of the \u201cPity and Terror\u201d exhibition at the Queen Sofia Museum, a celebration of its 80th anniversary. At the top of this painting, a light bulb in a lamp mimics the shape of a human eye. A screaming horse appears in the center of this painting that was created as a reaction to the bombing of a Basque village. The Spanish Civil War is the backdrop for, for the point, what artwork by Pablo Picasso?", "answer": "<b> Guernica</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During this war, John Pettyjohns won the first ever Victoria Cross for his heroism at the Battle of Inkerman. William Russell chronicled a cavalry attack on troops led by Colin Campbell during this war, and coined the phrase \u201cthin red line.\u201d A miscommunication at this war\u2019s Battle of Balaclava led to the ill-fated Charge of the Light Brigade. The Siege of Sevastopol took place in, for the point, what 1853 war between Russia and a British-French-Ottoman alliance?", "answer": "<b> Crimean</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Processing of this resource in Venezuela is dominated by PDVSA, which operates wells in the Maracaibo basin. For the point, name this finite resource which has been refined to create fossil fuels.", "answer": "crude<b> oil</b> (accept<b> petrol</b>eum)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "B\u00b4ela Kun started a short-lived Communist republic in this country, which fell apart after an invasion led by King Ferdinand. In this country, the Nazi-backed Arrow Cross party overthrew Miklos Horthy, who had been selected as regent following a series of revolutions. The Treaty of Trianon gave much of this country\u2019s territory to neighboring Romania in the aftermath of World War I. For the point, name this country that was once in a dual monarchy with Austria.", "answer": "<b> Hungary</b> (do not accept Austria-Hungary) Page 4", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a ballad, a worker from this country tells his captain that \u201ca man is nothing but a man.\u201d That worker from this country supposedly died with a hammer in his hand shortly after beating a machine in a rock-drilling contest. In a story from this country, a companion of Sourdough Sam bestows the name\u201cBabe\u201d on a massive blue ox that he finds and adopts. For the point, name this country that developed folklore about John Henry and Paul Bunyan.", "answer": "<b> United States</b> of<b> America</b> (accept either underlined portion; accept<b> US</b>A)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "A commander in this war allegedly chose to spare a town after its mayor was able to drink 3 liters of wine. This war\u2019s Battle of the Rain led to the death of Count Tilly and his replacement by Albrecht von Wallenstein. This war\u2019s Battle of Breitenfeld led many German states to ally with a Protestant coalition, but the Battle of Lutzen led to the death of that coalition\u2019s greatest commander, Gustavus Adolphus. For the point, name this European religious conflict that lasted from 1618 to 1648.", "answer": "<b> Thirty Years\u2019</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A leader of this country mistakenly believed it had been recognized by the Holy See after Ambrose Dudley Mann mistranslated a letter from Pope Pius IX. Two diplomats from this country were illegally seized from a British ship in the<em> Trent</em> Affair. This country attempted to persuade France and the United Kingdom to support it in a war against its northern neighbor by engaging in cotton diplomacy. For the point, name this rebellious state that was defeated in the American Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Confederate States</b> of America (accept<b> CSA</b>; accept The<b> Confederacy</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This island is home to the 12th Space Warning Squadron, which operates near Saunders Island at Thule Air Base, the US Air Force\u2019s northernmost air base. Harry Truman offered to buy this island for one hundred million dollars in 1946; in 2019 via tweet, Donald Trump offered to buy this island, prompting ridicule from the Prime Minister of Denmark. For the point, name this largest island in the world.", "answer": "<b> Greenland</b> (or<b> Kalaallit Nunaat</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Members of this profession were managed by lanistas who trained them at ludi. Septimius Severus banned women from this profession after watching men cat-call them at the Antiochene Olympic Games. The Third Servile War began after a group of people in this profession fled Capua. In staged damnatio ad bestias, members of this profession clashed with lions. For the point, name this profession whose members often fought each other in the Colosseum.", "answer": "<b> gladiator</b>s (prompt on \u201cslaves\u201d) Page 5", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The area surrounding this natural feature is the longtime ancestral home of the Havasupai people. In 1869, the Powell Geographic Expedition completed a survey of the Green River and the entirety of this natural feature. Troops under Francisco Vazquez de Coronado became the first Europeans to reach this natural feature in the 1540s. A skywalk overlooks the West Rim of this feature in Eagle Point, Arizona. For the point, name this gorge carved by the Colorado River.", "answer": "<b> Grand Canyon</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In this century, Europe\u2019s oldest alliance, between the nations of Portugal and England, was signed. Timur established his namesake dynasty in Central Asia in this century, and Mansa Musa undertook his hajj to Mecca in this century. Edward III claimed the French throne in this century, starting what would become the Hundred Years\u201d War. The Black Death peaked in, for the point, what century?", "answer": "<b> 14th</b> century AD (or<b> 1300s</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}